A Guide to the Warren Weaver papers FA419
Rockefeller Archive Center
Warren Weaver papers
1912-1978
Rockefeller Archive Center
Weaver, Warren (1894-1978)
Rockefeller Foundation
Alfred P. Sloan Foundation
Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center
FA419
32 Cubic Feet
Biographical/Historical note
Warren Weaver (b. July 7, 1894, d. November 24, 1978) was a scientist, mathematician and science administrator, best known as one of the pioneers of machine translation and as an advocate and supporter of science in all its forms.
Warren Weaver was born in the town of Reedsburg Wisconsin, son of Isaiah Weaver and Kittie Belle (Stupfell) Weaver. Isaiah Weaver was a drugstore owner and it was through his dealings as a druggist that Warren was first introduced to science. During one of his father's annual toy buying trips to Chicago in preparation for the holiday season at the drugstore, he bought 7-yearold Warren a $1 Ajax motor powered by a single dry cell battery. Warren took it apart, rebuilt it and began tinkering with its components and mechanics. With curiosity and imagination, a life in science was born. "I didn't know whether such activity was called science or engineering or what...but I decided right then that whatever this was, I wanted it" said Weaver.1
Warren Weaver served as a 2nd Lieutenant in the Air Service during World War I from 1917- 1919. Weaver's formal education was attained at the University of Wisconsin-Madison where he earned a Bachelor of Science degree in 1916, a civil engineering degree in 1917, and later a Ph.D. in 1921. It was also at the University of Wisconsin where Warren met and fell in love with fellow student Mary Hemenway. The couple was married on September 4, 1919 and had two children Warren Jr. and Helen Hemenway. Mary became Warren's staunchest supporter and at times his critic as well. "She had strong convictions and defended them with reason and logic, and held her own in family discussions. Warren learned to depend in many ways on Mary, whose wise counsel was invaluable."2
In 1917 Weaver began his teaching career as an Assistant Professor of Mathematics at Throop Polytechnic Institute, Pasadena, CA, renamed the California Institute of Technology in 1919.
In 1920 Weaver returned to the University of Wisconsin and assumed the position of Assistant Professor of Mathematics, 1920-25; Associate Professor of Mathematics, 1925-28; and Mathematics Professor and Department Chairmen, 1928-1932.
Throughout his career Weaver contributed many papers and articles to math and science journals. Several of his early writings are "The Pressure of Sound" (1920), "The Kinetic Theory of Magnetism" (1920), his collaboration with Max Mason "The Settling of Small Particles in a Fluid" (1924) and the influential books Elementary Mathematical Analysis (1925) and The Electromagnetic Field (with Max Mason), University of Chicago Press, 1929.
Trained as a mathematician, in 1932 Weaver was offered the Directorships of the newly established Natural Sciences Division of the Rockefeller Foundation and the General Education Board. "Inherent in Weaver's responsibilities with the Foundation was the necessity to travel widely, and to become intimately familiar with a broad spectrum of scientists and their laboratories here [in the United States] and abroad."3 At the start of this endeavor he feared his lack of competence in the wide range of sciences now under his care, for which he said, "I was convinced that the great wave of the future....was in the biological sciences."4
At the Rockefeller Foundation, Weaver was responsible for approving grants for major projects in a variety of natural sciences including molecular engineering, genetics, and later agriculture and medical research. In many ways his primary job was to identify, support and encourage young scientists and foster their development. Often this required Weaver to forecast and select scientists he believed were or would be innovators in their respective fields. "Beginning with 1933 Dr. Weaver saw clearly that science was being degraded in some regions of Europe and was a powerful factor in recruiting for American mathematics a large number of scholars from the various European countries."5
He studied intensely to expand his knowledge base to a broad range of sciences in order to make sound judgments and fulfill the obligations of the RF directorship, particularly in his first programs in quantitative biology. He sought to obtain greater support for the development of experimental biology including biochemistry, cellular physiology, embryology and genetics. Weaver "passionately believed that compartmentalization of any science weakened its total impact, and that only interdisciplinary effort would result in solid progress."6 Therefore he sought to eliminate the traditional barriers between scientific disciplines and advocated crossdisciplinary studies in order to more fully dissect, diagnose, and address the world's problems. "The coming of age of biology will be seriously impeded unless the circumstances of encouragement and support are favorable for the breaking down of old orthodox compartments in science, unless all the tools and techniques of the physicist, the chemist and the mathematician can be brought effectively to bear"7
In 1943 the Rockefeller Foundation added agriculture to the Natural Sciences program. The agricultural program had two primary objectives: 1. To cooperate with foreign governments in agricultural research, such as those programs instituted in Mexico and Columbia "with the practical aim of using science to improve both the quality and quantity of basic food crops;" 2. The development of agricultural science through the encouragement of advanced research and the training of personnel.8
Weaver practiced what he preached. He often sought to break the traditional barriers of scientific research by calling upon his broad spectrum of personal and professional colleagues and acquaintances from varying fields and expertise to seek collaborators for various personal projects and writings. He was co-author, with Claude E. Shannon, of The Mathematical Theory of Communication, University of Illinois Press, in 1949, often considered a landmark work in the field of communication. Shannon's essay focused primarily on the engineering aspects of the theory, while Weaver's "Some Recent Contributions to the Mathematical Theory of Communication" offered a philosophical discussion of the implications of the theory written with language accessible to a greater audience. Weaver "believed that communication leads to understanding which in turn leads to social progress."9 Later collaborations included U.S. Philanthropic Foundations: Their History, Structure, Management and Record, (1967) in which Weaver utilized his knowledge of Foundations and his vast experience as an administrator in the third sector to collaborate with George Wells Beadle and others.
Weaver's dedication to science was possibly only equaled by his profound dedication to the United States and the ideals of democratic society. "Called upon to return to his original interests in applied mathematics during World War II, Weaver directed government research projects in the Office of Scientific Research and Development. From July 1940 until December 1942 he served as Chairman of Section D-2, the Fire Control Division, of the National Defense Research Committee, and from 1943-1946 as Chief of the Applied Mathematics Panel, an organization of over 200 mathematicians and statisticians working on a wide variety of military problems. As early as 1941, Weaver had served on an official scientific mission, under James Bryant Conant, to investigate British weapons development."10
"As Chief of the Applied Mathematics Panel of the National Defense Research Committee...Dr. Weaver rendered service beyond all praise. Through his insight and diplomatic skill, he was able to convince the armed forces that mathematics is vital in the solution of many urgent problems of defense and offense. Because of his wide knowledge of, and remarkable ability in, the applications of mathematics he was successful in rallying a host of members of the [American Mathematical] Society to join him in exploring problems remote from their own fields. In the various events which resulted in mathematics emerging from the war with greatly enhanced prestige, he was a notable leader"11
For his outstanding service in connection with the development of anti-aircraft fire control devices (prediction computers, and controlling servomechanisms) and for bombsights and computing sites for use in air-to-air combat, Weaver was awarded the Medal for Merit (1948), the highest honor a civilian can receive from the United States. He also received the King's Medal for Service in the Cause of Freedom (1948) from Britain and he was named an Officer of the Legion of Honor in France (1950).12
After World War II, Weaver continued his civilian service in a variety of capacities including but not limited to: membership on the Research Advisory Panel of the War Department, 1946-1947; Chairman of the Naval Research Advisory Panel, 1946-1947; and Chairman of the Basic Research Group, Research and Development Board, Department of Defense, 1952-1953.
Weaver's dedication to promoting the international understanding of science, as well as his cross-disciplinary approach and brilliant analytical mind were clearly on display in his memorandum "Translation" of July 15, 1949 in which he wrote "There is no need to do more than mention the obvious fact that a multiplicity of languages impedes cultural interchange between the peoples of the earth, and is a serious deterrent to international understanding. The present memorandum, assuming the validity and importance of this fact, contains some comments and suggestions bearing on the possibility of contributing at least something to the worldwide translation problem through the use of electronic computers of great capacity, flexibility and speed. The suggestions of this memorandum will surely be incomplete and naïve, and may well be patently silly to an expert in the field – for the author is certainly not such."13 With his unassuming manner, and common language analogies, Weaver then proceeded to present quite possibly the single most influential publication in the early history of the field of machine translation, and as he had hoped it served as a direct stimulus for research in the field.
In his career as a science administrator Weaver served many foundations and philanthropic endeavors including but not limited to the General Education Board (where he served as Director, Division of Natural Sciences,1932-1937); the Rockefeller Foundation (Director, Division of Natural Sciences, 1932-1955; Director, Division of Science and Agriculture, 1951- 1955, Vice President for Natural and Medical Sciences, 1955-1959); Alfred P. Sloan Foundation (Trustee, 1956-1967; Vice President, 1959-1964; Consultant Scientific Affairs, 1964-1978, Member Executive Committee, 1956-1967; Honorary Trustee, 1967-1978); Salk Institute of Biological Studies, San Diego, CA (Trustee, Chairman of the Board, Non-Resident Fellow); Sloan Kettering Institute (Member, Board of Scientific Consultants, 1951-1954; Trustee, 1954- 1967; Chairman, Committee on Scientific Policy, 1955-1959; Member, Executive Committee, 1956-1967; Vice President, 1958-1959); Memorial Hospital (Member, Board, Memorial Center for Cancer and Allied Diseases, 1958-1960; Vice Chairman of the Board, Chairman of the Committee on Scientific Policy, Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, 1960-1967; Member, Executive Committee, Memorial Hospital for Cancer and Allied Diseases, 1960-1967). Weaver also served on a variety of councils and committees including but not limited to the National Advisory Cancer Council USPHS, 1957-1960 and as a member of the Governor's Committee on Hospital Costs (N.Y.), 1964-1965. Weaver was President and Chairman of the Board of the American Philosophical Society, 1955. He also served as Member, Vice-Chairman, and Member of the Executive Committee of the Health Research Council N.Y.C., 1958-1960; Director and President of the Public Health Research Institute, N.Y.C, 1961-1963; and as a Member of the National Science Board, National Science Foundation, 1956-1960.
"Warren Weaver's ideas about policy in foundation support of scientific work appeared to be contradictory. In his main service as a director of the Rockefeller Foundation, he developed such applications of science as quantitative biology, better corn for Mexico, and better rice for India. In his membership on the Science Board of the National Science Foundation he came down strong for support of fundamental research. As the director of the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation his policy was to support chosen men or women, neither with a particular mission in applied science nor with commitment to fundamental research, and he assisted in the support of an institute of applied mathematics at NYU. He did not try to resolve these apparent contradictions by any abstract principles, which he distrusted as being too inflexible. Instead, he believed that such diverse aims were not only tolerable but desirable. It only required that the one who made the choices in the foundation have a good mind and training and be willing to use them with the help of the best obtainable expert advice."14
Along with communication, Weaver's greatest personal research interest lay with the mathematical theory of probability. It was his belief that all scientists are deeply concerned with probability. "For a vast range of cases in which it is entirely impossible for science to answer the question 'Is this statement true?' probability theory does furnish the basis for judgment as to how likely it is that the statement is true. It is probability which, in an important fraction of cases, enables man[kind] to resolve the paradoxical dilemma pointed out by Samuel Butler: 'Life is the art of drawing sufficient conclusions from insufficient premises."15 Early in his career Weaver tackled the matter of probability with several writings including "The Reign of Probability" (1930) and "Probability, Rarity, Interest and Surprise" (1948) both published in the Scientific Monthly. Weaver's pursuit to share his passion for probability with the people of the world culminated with Lady Luck: The Theory of Probability published in 1963. It is a witty fun introduction to probability theory with more than 40 illustrations by Peg Hosford and no advanced understanding of mathematics required. Along with his extensive knowledge of the subject, Weaver shares his personality, and his joy and love for mathematics. Possibly his greatest talent and most momentous achievement was his innate ability to communicate complicated mathematical and scientific concepts to children and the general public in a manner that clearly and distinctly brought these concepts into everyday life. Combined with his teaching talents he had built and refined this skill advocating for research support of young and often unproven scientists while at the Rockefeller Foundation, and he perfected it with the innovative and imaginative Lady Luck.
Weaver was elected President of the American Association for the Advancement of Science in 1954. He was named a fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences (1958). He received the Public Welfare Medal from the National Academy of Sciences in 1957 and the first Arches of Science Award from the Pacific Science Center in 1965 for outstanding contributions to the public understanding of the meaning of science to contemporary men and women. In the same year, UNESCO presented Weaver with its international literary award, the Kalinga Prize for distinguished contributions to the popular understanding of science and exceptional skill in presenting scientific ideas to lay people.
Among his many memberships included: the American Mathematics Society, Mathematics Association of America, American Philosophical Society, American Society of Naturalists, American Society of Symbolic Logic, Council Library Resources (dir. 1956-59), National Academy of Sciences, Corr. Member, Chr. Michelsens Institutt (CMI), Bergen, Norway, as well as the Cosmos Club (Washington, DC) and the Century Association (N.Y.C.).
Weaver was also an aficionado of the storyteller Lewis Carroll and his seminal work of fantasy Alice's Adventures in Wonderland. Richard Magat wrote in 1959 "Alice in Wonderland was the first book Warren Weaver ever owned. His mother read it to him before he could read it himself. He has never since escaped the thrall of Lewis Carroll's whimsy. Indeed he has not tried to escape; he has been a quite willing captive to a form of communication that reaches everyone"16 Carroll's educational training and academic work were in the field of mathematics within which he published many works under his given name Charles L. Dodgson. Weaver was actually "very much like Carroll in his ability to communicate to all sorts of people his ideas about the exceedingly strange things of the everyday"17
Weaver owned an extensive collection of Carroll's writings, now held at the University of Texas, and he wrote several articles dedicated to Carroll's work as well as the book Alice in Many Tongues (1964) devoted to 160 translations of Alice in Wonderland in 42 languages. Weaver "continued his study of science and communication throughout his life, not only to do well in his job as supporter of science but also to become a remarkable interpreter of science and mathematics to the public. He proved that, if a mathematician puts his mind to it, mathematics is a very good base – perhaps the best – from which to become broadly educated in science and the humanities. By the time he retired, Warren Weaver was as knowledgeable a scientific generalist as we had in this country, and as wise a director of philanthropy as we had"18
1 Magat, Richard. "Everyman's Scientist: Dr. Warren Weaver", Saturday Review, May 2, 1959. 2 Harrar, J.G. "Warren Weaver". Year Book of the American Philosophical Society, p.113-117, 1979. 3 Harrar, J.G. "Warren Weaver". Year Book of the American Philosophical Society, p.113-117, 1979. 4 Duren, William L. Jr. Notices of the American Mathematical Society, vol. 26, no. 3, April 1979. 5 Resolution of the Board of Trustees of the American Mathematical Society, January 17, 1948, Folder 132, Warren Weaver Papers, RAC. 6 Harrar, J.G. "Warren Weaver". Year Book of the American Philosophical Society, p.113-117, 1979. 7 Barnard, Chester I. Science, vol 117, no. 3034, pages 174-176, February 20, 1953. 8 Barnard, Chester I. Science, vol 117, no. 3034, pages 174-176, February 20, 1953. 9 Harrar, J.G. "Warren Weaver". Year Book of the American Philosophical Society, p.113-117, 1979. 10 Barnard, Chester I. Science, vol 117, no. 3034, pages 174-176, February 20, 1953. 11 Resolution of the Board of Trustees of the American Mathematical Society, January 17, 1948, Folder 132, Warren Weaver Papers, RAC. 12 Barnard, Chester I. Science, vol 117, no. 3034, pages 174-176, February 20, 1953. 13 Weaver, Warren. "Translation", July15 1949, Folder 476, Warren Weaver papers, RAC. 14 Duren, William L., Jr. Notices of the American Mathematical Society, vol. 26, no. 3, April 1979. 15 Scientific American, 183, 47, October 1950. 16 Magat, Richard. "Everyman's Scientist: Dr. Warren Weaver", Saturday Review, May 2, 1959. 17 Magat, Richard. "Everyman's Scientist: Dr. Warren Weaver", Saturday Review, May 2, 1959. 18 Duren, William L., Jr. Notices of the American Mathematical Society, vol. 26, no. 3, April 1979.
Scope and Contents note
The Warren Weaver papers consist of correspondence, memoranda, reports, speeches, manuscripts, articles, reprints, photographs and a selection of oversized materials including awards, citations and degrees.
The collection documents Weaver's life as a teacher, author, mathematician, administrator and scientist. It sheds light on his vast interests and knowledge as well as the relationships he developed, and the respect he garnered, from an extensive network of friends, colleagues, academicians and acquaintances in the fields of mathematics, science, philanthropy, the armed forces and government.
The papers demonstrate Weaver's brilliant analytical mind, his wit, his humor, his capacity for logic and deductive reasoning, his lifelong commitment to science and communication and his extraordinary ability to express complex concepts in common language to share the magic of science with the general populous.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Helen Weaver, Warren Weaver's daughter, donated these records to the Rockefeller Archive Center in April 2001. The Archive Center received the collection in multiple accessions including but not limited to those made in January 1997, November 2000 and March 2001 (Accessions 1997:002, 2001:015, 2005:008 and 2009:013).
Custodial History
Various folders or items within the collection may contain informational notes handwritten by Weaver's daughter Helen while she was reviewing the records and preparing them for shipment to RAC.
Arrangement note
The Warren Weaver papers are arranged into 13 series: 1. Correspondence, 1912-1978 (5.5 cu. ft.); 2. Biographical, 1932-1978 (0.5 cu. ft.); 3. Rockefeller Foundation, 1933-1961 (2.5 cu. ft.); 4. Travel, 1932-1961 (1.5 cu. ft.); 5. Salk Institute for Biological Studies, 1961-1973 (4 cu. ft.); 6. Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, 1957-1974 (3.5 cu. ft.); 7. Sloan-Kettering Institute, 1959-1973 (0.8 cu. ft.); 8. General Files, 1932-1979 (3.5 cu. ft.); 9. Speeches & Articles, 1937-c.1966 (1 cu. ft.); 10. Awards, Citations and Degrees, 1936-1969 (2 cu. ft.); 11. Manuscripts, 1963-1965 (2 cu. ft.); 12. Reprints, 1920-1987 (Bulk: 1932-1977) (6 cu. ft.); 13. Photographs & Special Formats.
The majority of the records are arranged as received by RAC. Arrangement of the material within folders is also as received, primarily in a loose reverse chronological order (unless otherwise noted).
Related Archival Materials note
Related Archival Material available at RAC
1. Rockefeller Foundation Records (particularly those records documenting the Division of Natural Sciences (1932-1955), the Division of Sciences and Agriculture (1951-1955) and the Medical Sciences (1955-1959).
2. Warren Weaver Diaries, 1932-1959 (Rockefeller Foundation, RG 12 Officers' Diaries)
3. Warren Weaver Oral Histories: Oral History Research Office, Columbia University, 1961; Mexican Agricultural Program, 1966 (Rockefeller Foundation, RG 13 Oral Histories)
4. Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center records
Related Archival Materials note
Related Material at other Archival Repositories
1. Warren Weaver Papers, 1928-1932 (0.3 cu. ft.), University of Wisconsin.
2. Lewis Carroll (Charles Dodgson), Warren Weaver Collection, University of Texas.
Agricultural administration; Administration; Distribution (Probability theory); Mathematics; Applied mathematics; Mathematical statistics; Mass Communications; Science -- Physical and Mathematics; Education; Mathematics -- Study and teaching
- Correspondence, 1912-1978; 1; 5.5 Cubic Feet
  Arrangement